Guide to the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences Audiovisual Collection MC.387
New York University Archives
Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences Audiovisual Collection
1958-2011
New York University Archives
Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences
Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences. Library
MC.387
10 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 5 LP boxes, and 2 card boxes
51 videocassettes (vhs)
4 videocassettes (betacamsp)
2 videocassettes (u-matic)
3 videocassettes (minidv)
12 videoreels (1 inch)
43 Disks in Sony XDCAM Professional Discs
1 audiocassette
11 sound tape reels in 1/4" open reel audio reels
205 Gigabytes in 1,953 computer files
This collection includes audiovisual and born-digital recordings of events at the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences, including lectures given by faculty and guests, symposia, anniversary celebrations, and the Warren Weaver Hall Dedication Ceremony; interviews with scholars and faculty including Ernest Courant, Herbert Morawetz, and Harold Shapiro; early forays into animation, likely by the Computer Science Program; and promotional materials, such as brochures, promotional images, and a 75th Anniversary video. The Courant Institute initially grew from the Graduate School of Arts and Science's Department of Mathematics and serves as New York Unviersity's mathematics research school.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Meg Smith to the New York University Archives from the Courant Institute in the summer of 2023 when the Courant Institute Library closed. The accession number associated with this transfer is 2023.052.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical Note
The Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences serves as New York University's mathematics research school. It grew from the Graduate School of Arts and Science's Department of Mathematics, which began to focus on research projects following Richard Courant's appointment in 1935. The Institute was named the Institute for Mathematics and Mechanics in 1946. In that year and 1954, research projects led to the establishment of the Division of Wave Propagation and Applied Mathematics and the Division of Magnetofluid Dynamics, respectively. NYU's first computer was installed at the Courant Institute in 1952, and its Computer Science program rapidly developed to include research on programming languages, computer graphics, parallel architectures, and theory. In 1965 the Institute was renamed after Richard Courant and moved to the newly constructed Warren Weaver Hall, where a majority of its activities still take place. The Division of Computational Fluid Dynamics was created in 1978.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact [New York University Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Access to born-digital material is available via streaming to the NYU network. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes audiovisual and born-digital recordings of events at the Courant Institute, including lectures given by faculty and guests, symposia, anniversary celebrations, and the Warren Weaver Hall Dedication Ceremony; interviews with scholars and faculty, including Ernest Courant, Herbert Morawetz, and Harold Shapiro; early forays into animation, likely by the Computer Science Program; and promotional materials, such as brochures, promotional images, and a 75th Anniversary video. Lectures and discussions explore topics such as improvisational animation, automation and robotics, operating systems, and fractal interfaces.
Education, Higher -- New York (N.Y.); Mathematics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Animation; Computer science.; VHS; Video recordings.; Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences. Library
- Record #8, March 23, 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0001)
- Record #9, circa 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0002)
- Record #3, March 21, 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0003)
- Warren Weaver Hall Dedication Ceremonies, Reel #1, March 29, 1965 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0004)
- Warren Weaver Hall Dedication Ceremonies, Reel #2, March 29, 1965 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0005)
- Record #1, March 21, 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0006)
- Record #2, March 21, 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0007)
- Record #4, March 21, 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0008)
- Record #5, March 22, 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0009)
- Record #6, March 22, 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0010)
- Record #7, March 22, 1966 (Box 1, Quarter inch audio reel 387_0011)
- "Pad" by Ken Perlin, circa 1990s (Box 1, Vhs 387_0012)
- Courant Birthday -- Morawetz Family in Snow, circa 1958 (Box 1, Vhs 387_0013)
- "Derham Theory: Retrospective" Lecture, R. Bott, 1994 (Box 1, Vhs 387_0014)
- Mark Kac Talk, July 26, 1972 (Box 1, Betacam sp 387_0015)
- Unlabeled Tape, Undated (Box 1, Betacam sp 387_0016)
- Mark Kac Talk, July 24, 1972 (Box 1, Betacam sp 387_0017)
- Unlabeled Tape, Undated (Box 1, Betacam sp 387_0018)
- "Danse" -- New Version in Two Sequences, circa 1990s (Box 2, Vhs 387_0019)
- "Danse Interactif" and "Improvisational Animation", circa 1990s (Box 2, Vhs 387_0020)
- "Images from the Microscope" by Ken Perlin, circa 1990s (Box 2, Vhs 387_0021)
- "An Integrated Approach to Motion and Sound" Animation Examples, Undated (Box 2, Vhs 387_0022)
- "Toolglass and Magic Lenses: The See-Through Interface", Undated (Box 2, Vhs 387_0023)
- "Sid and the Penguins" NYU-CAT, circa 1990s (Box 2, Vhs 387_0024)
- LMA Camera 2, Fall, 2004 (Box 2, Minidv 387_0025)
- LIPA Workshop, Undated (Box 2, Minidv 387_0026)
- Hackathon Evanworth, April 9, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0027)
- #3, March 25, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0028)
- Courant #2, March 25, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0029)
- #3, March 23, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0030)
- Courant #1, April 6, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0031)
- B-roll Animation Elements, March 29, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0032)
- #3, March 24, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0033)
- Courant #1, April 8, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0034)
- Courant #1, April 4, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0035)
- Courant #2, April 1, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0036)
- Percy Deitt Interview, March 24, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0037)
- Courant #4, April 1, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0038)
- Courant #1, April 1, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0039)
- B-roll Disc 2, April 19, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0040)
- #2, April 8, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0041)
- Courant #2, April 7, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0042)
- Courant #2, April 6, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0043)
- Tayn Extras, Undated (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0044)
- Courant Exteriors, October 29, 2010 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0045)
- #2A, March 24, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0046)
- #3, April 7, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0047)
- #2, March 23, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0048)
- Courant #3, April 8, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0049)
- Courant #4, March 31, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0050)
- Courant #4, March 25, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0051)
- #4, March 24, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0052)
- #4, April 4, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0053)
- Courant #2, April 4, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0054)
- B-roll #2, March 29, 2011 (Box 2, Xdcam 387_0055)
- Courant #1, March 19, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0056)
- Courant #1, April 6, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0057)
- Courant #3, April 7, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0057)
- Courant #3, April 4, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0058)
- Courant #3, April 1, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0059)
- Courant #3, March 31, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0060)
- Exteriors, October 29, 2010 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0061)
- Courant #1, March 31, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0062)
- Mike Shelley and Richard Cole B-roll, March 28, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0063)
- Courant #1, March 25, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0064)
- Courant #1, March 23, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0065)
- TBC #4, March 23, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0066)
- TBC #1, March 24, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0066)
- Courant #2, March 28, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0067)
- Courant #5, April 4, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0068)
- Courant #2, March 31, 2011 (Box 3, Xdcam 387_0069)
- Unlabeled Tape, Undated (Box 3, Vhs 387_0070)
- "Operating System" #5, Waverly Hall, October 12, 1993 (Box 3, Vhs 387_0071)
- Warren Weaver Hall, NYU #6, October 19, 1993 (Box 3, Vhs 387_0072)
- "Operating System", September 28, 1993 (Box 3, Vhs 387_0073)
- "Operating Systems", November 16, 1993 (Box 3, Vhs 387_0074)
- 20th Annual Courant Lee, April 2, 2003 (Box 3, Vhs 387_0075)
- "Preserving the Legacy: The First 40 Years", Undated (Box 3, Vhs 387_0076)
- Memorial in Memory of Fritz John, Courant Institute, September 30, 1994 (Box 3, Vhs 387_0077)
- "Jack Schwartz -- A Brief History", May 19, 1995 (Box 3, Vhs 387_0078)
- "Calculus Follies" Holiday Lecture by Peter Lax, December, 1997 (Box 3, Vhs 387_0079)
- "Wild to be Wreckage Forever" Cindy Stillwell, January 18, 1996 (Box 4, U-matic 387_0080)
- "Improvisational Animations," Ken Perlin, May 1, 1993 (Box 4, U-matic 387_0081)
- Randy Smith Self Video, Undated (Box 4, Vhs 387_0082)
- PAD++, NYU Center for Advanced Technology, January, 1997 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0083)
- Scratch Blend Footage, circa 1990s (Box 4, Vhs 387_0084)
- "Operating System," Partha Dasgupta, Warren Weaver, November 30, 1993 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0085)
- "Stochastic Partial Differential Equations" Lecture by Pierre-Louis Lions, April 3, 2003 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0086)
- David P. Ruelle, McLaughlin, D., D'Agostino Hall, March 6, 1997 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0087)
- Women in Mathematical Sciences Connected to Industry, February 23-25, 1996 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0088)
- H. Keller Courant Lecture, 1999 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0089)
- Philip Anderson, October 9, 1997 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0090)
- L.C. Evans Lecture, 2002 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0091)
- Warren Weaver Hall, December 14, 1999 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0092)
- R. Penrose, Dave McLaughlin, Warren Weaver, December 11, 1996 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0093)
- Sloan Colloquium -- Professor Elliott Lieb, Princeton University, April 25, 1997 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0094)
- "Pad" and "Danse Interactif" by Ken Perlin, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Vhs 387_0095)
- Richard Courant's Lecture at Yale, January 13, 1964 (Box 4, Audiocassette 387_0096)
- Courant Holiday Lecture, December 12, 2008 (Box 4, Minidv 387_0097)
- Ken Perlin, Asst. Professor of Computer Science, Undated (Box 5, Vhs 387_0098)
- "Fractal Interfaces for Collaborative Work," Ken Perlin, NYU, June, 1992 (Box 5, Vhs 387_0099)
- Proc. Animation Demo, Undated (Box 5, Vhs 387_0100)
- "Sig and the Penguins" Electronic Theater Performance, 1998 (Box 5, Vhs 387_0101)
- "Pad - Improv - Nuance," Ken Perlin, 1998 (Box 5, Vhs 387_0102)
- "Scratch" by Ken Perlin, circa 1990s (Box 5, Vhs 387_0103)
- Ken Perlin Talk, Undated (Box 5, Vhs 387_0104)
- "Eternal Gaze", Undated (Box 5, Vhs 387_0105)
- Football Animation, October 11, 1995 (Box 5, Vhs 387_0106)
- ET, June 24, 2004 (Box 5, Vhs 387_0107)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Herbert J. Bernstein, September, 1985 (Box 6, 1 inch video reel 387_0108)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," John C. Hopcroft, September, 1985 (Box 6, 1 inch video reel 387_0109)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Russell H. Taylor, September, 1985 (Box 6, 1 inch video reel 387_0110)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Paul K. Wright, September, 1985 (Box 7, 1 inch video reel 387_0111)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Michael Brady, September, 1985 (Box 7, 1 inch video reel 387_0112)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," David A. Kapilow, September, 1985 (Box 7, 1 inch video reel 387_0113)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," G. L. Miller, September, 1985 (Box 8, 1 inch video reel 387_0114)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Azriel Rosenfeld, September, 1985 (Box 8, 1 inch video reel 387_0115)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Tomas Lozano-Perez, September, 1985 (Box 9, 1 inch video reel 387_0116)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Jacob T. Schwartz, September, 1985 (Box 9, 1 inch video reel 387_0117)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Joseph L. Mundy, September, 1985 (Box 10, 1 inch video reel 387_0118)
- "Symposium on Factory Automation and Robotics," Robert A. Frosch, September, 1985 (Box 10, 1 inch video reel 387_0119)
- Courant Institute Interviews Herbert Kranzer, October 22, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_1)
- Courant Institute Interviews Eugene Isaacson, circa 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_2)
- Courant Institute Conference Day 2 Room 109, 80th Birthday Lax + Nirenbereg, Undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_3)
- Courant Institute Conference Dr. Shmuel Agmon, Undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_4)
- Courant Institute Interviews Shapiro, November 22, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_5)
- "Gottingen and New York -- Reflections on a Life in Mathematics -- Richard Courant", September 30, 1986 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_6)
- Courant Institute Interviews Ernest Courant, Undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_7)
- Courant Pneuli Memorial Symposium, May 8, 2010 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_8)
- Courant Pneuli Memorial Symposium, May 9, 2010 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_9)
- Courant Institute Interviews Herbert Morawetz, December 13, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_10)
- Memorial Conference in Honor of Paul Garabedian, Memorial Service, December 4, 2010 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_11)
- Richard Courant Speech, Yale Medical School, 1964 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_12)
- 75th Anniversary Video -- "75 Years of Achievement", 1960-2010 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_13)
- Memorial for Jack Schwartz, March 27, 2009 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_14)
- Courant Institute Event B-roll, October 28, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_15)
- Courant Institute Interviews Room 1314, October 28, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_16)
- "The Mathematician and the River" with Prof. Eugene Isaacson, 1960 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_17)
- "Virtual Interactive Puppetry", Undated (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_18)
- "Culture and Cognition" Presentation, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_19)
- "Ocean Temperature Probe Deployed by Helicopter" Photos and Videos by David Holland, June, 2007 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_20)
- "Second Course in Calculus" Digital Project, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_21)
- 75th Anniversary Video -- Release Forms, 2015 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_22)
- CIMS Brochure Images by Matthew Asselin, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_23)
- Courant Library -- Administrative Files, 2011-2015 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_24)
- Courant Scans, 2011-2012 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_25)
- Course Reserves, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_26)
- Exchange Program -- Administrative Files, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_27)
- Historical Images and Brochure Cover, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_28)
- Ken Perlin Academy Award Images, 2002 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_29)
- London Butterfly Performance Pics, 2002 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_30)
- Luneberg Digital Project, 2015 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_31)
- MW NYU Int., March 23-25, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_32)
- SETL Newsletters, 2012 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_33)
- Surgery Sim, 2002 (Box Electronic Records, E-records UA_MC_387_ER_34)